John M. House

9210 Rue Villieu, St-Leonard, QC, CANADA | □ (+1) 514-433-6181 | Mouse.john.m@gmail.com | Folder John M. House

Research Engineer

Summary.

Internationally recognized leader in the buildings community with over 25 years of experience conducting research in the public and private sectors to improve the control and operation of heating, ventilating, and air-conditioning (HVAC) systems. Contributions to the field of fault detection and diagnostics (FDD) are now incorporated in an industry guideline on high performance sequences of operation for HVAC systems, have been implemented in commercial products, and are commonly used as a benchmark for other FDD methods.

Expertise

- · Fault Detection and Diagnostics
- Control
- Optimization

- HVAC Equipment and Systems
- Modeling and Simulation
- · Energy Efficiency

Experience

Johnson Controls Montreal, QC Jan. 2008 - Jan. 2020

LEAD PRINCIPAL RESEARCH ENGINEER

Oct. 2011 - Jan. 2018

- Initiated and conducted research on control algorithms and fault detection and diagnostic techniques to improve the energy efficiency of heating, ventilating and air-conditioning (HVAC) systems in buildings.
- Responsible for development of Modelica-based dynamic HVAC system models and use of models for development of control algorithms and diagnostic tools.
- Initiated and guided university research collaborations supporting internal technology priorities.
- Provided industry outreach and technical guidance for research projects funded by ASHRAE and U.S. Department of Energy.

Principal Research Engineer Jan. 2008 - Oct. 2011

- Collaborated with research colleagues to develop and test algorithms for integrated control and fault detection, model-based economizer control and optimal start.
- Developed simulation platforms using Matlab, Simulink, Energy Plus, and Modelica-based tools and libraries to aid development and testing of control and fault detection algorithms.

Natural Resources Canada Varennes, QC Jan. 2005 - Jan. 2008

RESEARCH SCIENTIST: SECONDMENT ASSIGNMENT FROM THE IOWA ENERGY CENTER

- · Developed research plans and established collaborative research projects for Intelligent Buildings Group.
- · Conducted research on controls and diagnostics for HVAC and supermarket refrigeration systems.

Iowa Energy Center Ankeny, IA Nov. 2000 - Jan. 2008

RESEARCH ENGINEER

- Lead technical researcher of the National Building Controls Information Program.
- Conducted sponsored research and demonstration projects, and supported IEC funded research, related to building controls, fault detection and diagnostics, and commissioning for private industry and federal government.
- Represented the Iowa Energy Center on national initiatives, collaborations and committees related to building energy efficiency.
- Provided technical support and guidance for IEC-funded research projects.

National Institute of Standards and Technology

PRINCIPAL INVESTIGATOR / PROJECT LEADER

- Gaithersburg, MD Oct. 1994 Nov. 2000
- Conducted research related to the development and testing of fault detection and diagnostic (FDD) methods for HVAC systems. Led the development of APAR (Air-handling unit Performance Assessment Rules).
- Collaborated with staff at Johnson Controls, Inc. to perform simulation and laboratory testing of advanced control strategies and FDD methods.
- Participated in international collaborations to perform FDD research with the Korea Institute of Energy Research, the Scientific and Technical Building Centre in Paris, France, and members of the International Energy Agency (IEA) Annex 34 working group.
- Monitored sponsored research on FDD methods for rooftop units conducted at Purdue University.
- Served as the IEA Annex 34 country representative for the United States.

Internship Experience

The Dow Chemical Company

SUMMER RESEARCH INTERN

Developed an Excel application for multivariate statistical monitoring of continuous and batch processes.

NMC North Microelectronics

Beijing, China

Freeport, TX

Jun. 2008 - Jul. 2008

May 2010 - Aug. 2010

SUMMER ENGINEERING INTERN

· Developed a multivariate statistical application for monitoring the operation of a semiconductor manufacturing process.

Education

The University of Iowa: Iowa City, Iowa

DOCTOR OF PHILOSOPHY IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

1994

Ph.D. Dissertation: Optimal Control for HVAC and Building Systems

MASTER OF SCIENCE IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING

1988

• MS Thesis: Development of Two Optimal Control Methodologies for Thermal Systems

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE IN MECHANICAL ENGINEERING, WITH DISTINCTION

1987

Skills

Programming Modelica, Python, R, ŁTEX

Applications Dymola, Matlab, Simulink, EnergyPlus, Jupyter Notebook

Certifications

Introduction to Computer Science and Programming Using Python

MITx

Mar. 26, 2020

Credential ID: 48f759f8883c44b9a6a0bad569f95df4

Publications

Journal Papers

A method for setpoint alarming using a normalized index

Carlos F. Alcala, Timothy I. Salsbury

Control Engineering Practice 60.3 (2017) pp. 1–6. 2017

An extremum-seeking control method driven by input-output correlation

Timothy I Salsbury, John M House, Carlos F Alcala, Yaoyu Li

Journal of Process Control 58 (2017) pp. 106–116. Elsevier, 2017

Analysis and generalization of fault diagnosis methods for process monitoring

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Oin

Journal of Process Control 21.3 (2011) pp. 322-330. 2011

Generalized reconstruction-based contributions for output-relevant fault diagnosis with application to the tennessee eastman process

Gang Li, Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin, Donghua Zhou

Control Systems Technology, IEEE Transactions on 19.5 (Sept. 2011) pp. 1114–1127. 2011

Reconstruction-based contribution for process monitoring with kernel principal component analysis

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Industrial & Engineering Chemistry Research 49.17 (2010) pp. 7849–7857. 2010

Reconstruction-based contribution for process monitoring

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Automatica 45.7 (2009) pp. 1593-1600. 2009

Conference Papers

Self-optimizing Control of an Air Source Heat Pump

Zhongfan Zhao, Yaoyu Li, Timothy I Salsbury, Carlos F Alcala, John M House

2019 American Control Conference (ACC), 2019

Identification of a Self-Optimizing Control Structure from Normal Operating Data

Carlos F Alcala, Timothy I Salsbury, John M House

2019 American Control Conference (ACC), 2019

Decoupling Method for PI Controllers via Setpoint Modification Applied to HVAC Systems

Timothy I Salsbury, John M House, Carlos F Alcala

ASME 2018 Dynamic Systems and Control Conference, 2018

Reduction of Transmissions in Wireless Thermostats with Send-on-Delta Sampling and a Deadband Filter

Carlos F Alcala, Timothy I Salsbury

2018 Annual American Control Conference (ACC), 2018

Decoupling Method for PI Controllers via Setpoint Modification Applied to HVAC Systems

Timothy I. Salsbury, John M. House, Carlos F. Alcala

Proceedings of the Dynamic Systems and Control Conference, 2018

Reduction of Transmissions in Wireless Thermostats with Send-on-Delta Sampling and a Deadband Filter

C. F. Alcala, T. I. Salsbury

Proceedings of the 2018 Annual American Control Conference (ACC), 2018

Model Selection for Predicting the Return Time from Night Setback

John E Seem, John M House, Carlos F Alcala

Proceedings of the International High Performance Buildings Conference, 2016

Two new normalized EWMA-based indices for control loop performance assessment

Timothy I. Salsbury, Carlos F. Alcala

Proceedings of the American Control Conference (ACC), 2015

Monitoring of dynamic processes with subspace identification and principal component analysis

Ricardo Dunia Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Proceedings of the 8th IFAC International Symposium on Fault Detection, Supervision and Safety of Technical Processes, 2012, Mexico City, Mexico

Unified analysis of diagnosis methods for process monitoring

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Proceedings of the 7th IFAC International Symposium on Fault Detection, Supervision and Safety of Technical Processes, 2009, Barcelona, Spain

Unification of contribution analysis for process monitoring

Carlos F. Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Proceedings of the 2008 AIChE Annual Meeting, 2008, Philadelphia, USA

Reconstruction-based contribution for process monitoring

Carlos Alcala, S. Joe Qin

Proceedings of the 17th IFAC World Congress, 2008, Seoul, Korea